



Department of Rangeland, Wildlife and Fisheries Management - Texas A&M University, College Station, TX

▼ty.werdel@ag.tamu.edu | ★werdelwildlife.com | ②0000-0003-4023-9668 | ③tywerdel | 面tywerdel

2013

My research interests include the fields of Wildlife Management and Landscape Ecology. This work addresses questions that provide insight into the relationships between wildlife, native environments, and contemporary human-modified landscapes. I am also interested in software programming to advance my professional acumen, with this CV being compiled with code.

### Education

Ph.D. Horticulture and Natural Resources Manhattan, KS KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY 2022 M.S. Wildlife Sciences Brookings, SD SOUTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY 2017 **B.S. Rangeland and Wildlife Management** Chadron, NE

### Certifications \_\_\_\_\_

CHADRON STATE COLLEGE

Professional Certification in Data Analysis for Life Sciences (R) Online HARVARDX, HARVARD UNIVERSITY 2020 **GTA Certificate of Achievement in Professional Development** Manhattan, KS KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY 2020 **Faculty Exchange for Teaching Excellence** Manhattan, KS KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY 2020 **Associate Wildlife Biologist®** Online THE WILDLIFE SOCIETY 2016 **Graduate Certification in Geospatial Technology** Rapid City, SD SOUTH DAKOTA SCHOOL OF MINES AND TECHNOLOGY 2016 **Esri Academy ArcGIS (9 Certifications)** Online **ENVIRONMENTAL SYSTEMS RESEARCH INSTITUTE** 2021 **Project WILD/Project WILD Aquatic** Chadron, NE ASSOCIATION OF FISH AND WILDLIFE AGENCIES 2013

# Employment \_\_\_\_\_

Vice Chancellor's Postdoctoral Research Fellow	College Station, TX
Department of Rangeland, Wildlife, and Fisheries Management, Texas A&M University	2022 – Present
Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant	Manhattan, KS
DEPARTMENT OF HORTICULTURE AND NATURAL RESOURCES, KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY	2017 - 2022
Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant	Brookings, SD
DEPARTMENT OF NATURAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT, SOUTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY	2014 – 2017
GIS Technician	Scottsbluff, NE
North Platte Natural Resources District	2014 – 2014
Undergraduate Researcher	Socorro, NM
Sevilleta LTER Research Experience	2013 – 2013
Construction Foreman	Chadron, NE
Werdel Steel Construction	1998 – 2013

# **Teaching Experience**

Texas A&M University College Station, TX

Co-Instructor

2022

• Techniques of Wildlife Management, RWFM 408 & WFSC 638

**Kansas State University** 

Manhattan, KS 2017 - 2022

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

- Firearms Cartridges and Ballistics, WOEM 201
- Rifle and Handgun Range Design, Construction and Operations, WOEM 202
- Introduction to Wildlife and Outdoor Enterprise Management, WOEM 250
- Flora and Fauna of the Great Plains, WOEM 350
- Big Game Management, WOEM 555
- Waterfowl and Wetlands Management, WOEM 561
- Advanced Wildlife Habitat Management, WOEM 562

#### **South Dakota State University**

Brookings, SD

**GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT** 

2014 - 2017

• Introduction to Wildlife and Fisheries, WL 220

### **Publications**

#### Peer-Reviewed

- 5. Hessami, M.A., **T.J. Werdel**, S.J. Hoagland, and M.T. Kohl. **In-Press**. Melding Past, Present, and Future: The importance of tribal management in wildlife conservation and management. Chapter 1 in E. Gomez, C. Bishop, Ryder, and Organ eds. *Wildlife Management and Conservation in North America: An Overview*. Great River Learning of Dubuque, IA.
- Werdel, T.J., C.W. Piper, A.M. Ricketts, M.S. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. 2022. Scale-specific landscape effects impose range-limiting constraints on the distribution of swift fox. Landscape Ecology, 37(8), 2065–2079. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10980-022-01466-0
- 3. Werdel, T.J., J.A. Jenks, J.T. Kanta, C.P. Lehman, and T.J. Frink. 2021. Space use and movement patterns of translocated bighorn sheep. *Mammalian Biology*, 101(3),329–344. https://doi.org/10.1007/s42991-021-00107-4
- Werdel, T.J., J.A. Jenks, T.E. Besser, J.T. Kanta, C.P. Lehman, and T.J. Frink. 2019. Restoration of a bighorn sheep population impeded by Mycoplasma ovipneumoniae exposure. Restoration Ecology, 28(2), 387--395. https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1111/rec.13084
- Werdel, T.J., J.A. Jenks, T.E. Besser, J.T. Kanta, C.P. Lehman, and T.J. Frink. 2018. Survival of translocated bighorn sheep in the Deadwood region of the Black Hills, South Dakota. Northwestern Naturalist, 99(3),222–231. https://doi.org/10.1898/ NWN18-06.1

#### In-Revision/Review

- 6. Palomo-Muñoz, G, **T.J. Werdel**, C.W. Piper, M.S. Peek, A.M. Ricketts, and A.A Ahlers. **In-Revision**. Spatiotemporal distributions of mammals occurring in an agro-prairie ecosystem. *Ecology*.
- 5. **Werdel, T.J.**, C.W. Piper, A.M. Ricketts, M.S. Peek, and A.A Ahlers. **In-Revision**. Landscape-scale effects structure carnivore communities in an agro-prairie ecosystem. *Journal of Mammalogy*.
- 4. Piper, C.W., **T.J. Werdel**, M.S. Peek, A.M. Ricketts, D.S. Sullins, and A.A. Ahlers. **In-Revision**. Spatiotemporal distributions of mammals occurring in an agro-prairie ecosystem. *Journal of Mammalogy*.
- 3. **Werdel, T.J.**, J.A. Jenks, J.T. Kanta, C.P. Lehman, and T.J. Frink. **In-Review**. Resource selection and herbaceous biomass at foraging sites of translocated bighorn sheep. *Rangeland Ecology and Management*.
- 2. **Werdel, T.J.**, M. Fidino, C.W. Piper, A.M. Ricketts, M.S. Peek, and A.A Ahlers. **In-Review**. Landscape composition mediates spatiotemporal interactions among sympatric canids in a prairie ecosystem. *Ecological Applications*.
- 1. **Werdel, T.J.**, C.W. Piper, A.M. Ricketts, M.S. Peek, D.S. Sullins, and A.A Ahlers. **In-Review**. Strategic grassland conservation to improve conservation outcomes for swift foxes in a multi-use landscape. *Biological Conservation*.

# Honors & Awards

Total Awards (\$121,150)

Community Building Through Mentorship Conference Panel Travel Grant, The Wildlife Society	2022
Agriculture Dean and Director's Award for Graduate Student Research, Kansas State University	2022
Advancing Agricultural Science Opportunities for Native Americans Scholarship, AISES	2023
Robert Nunemacher Scholarship, Kansas State University	2023
Advancing Agricultural Science Opportunities for Native Americans Research Award, AISES	2020
Advancing Agricultural Science Opportunities for Native Americans Scholarship, AISES	2020
Lighting the Pathway to Faculty Careers for Natives in STEM, AISES	2020
College of Agriculture Graduate Student Recognition of Achievement, Kansas State University	2020
AISES Together Towards Tomorrow T3 Scholarship, AISES	2020
Gamma Sigma Delta, The Honor Society of Agriculture, Kansas State University	2019
AISES Travel Grant, AISES	2019
Advancing Agricultural Science Opportunities for Native Americans Scholarship, AISES	2019
Kansas State University Graduate Student Recognition of Achievement, Kansas State University	2019
College of Agriculture Graduate Student Recognition of Achievement, Kansas State University	2019
Inclusive Pedagogy Travel Grant, The Wildlife Society	2018
Life Membership Fund Scholarship, Wild Sheep Foundation	2018
Predoctoral Ford Fellowship, (Honorable Mention) Ford Foundation Fellowships Program	2018
Native Student Professional Development Grant, The Wildlife Society	2017
Launch Collegiate Business Pitch Competition, Kansas State University	2017
Native Student Professional Development Grant, The Wildlife Society	2016
Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society, South Dakota State University	2016
Excellence in Wildlife Management, Chadron State College	2013
<b>Platinum Eagle Award,</b> (Finalist) Chadron State College	2013
Gates Millennium Scholarship, Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation	2005
Scholastic Excellence in Engineering, University of Wyoming	2005
Scholars Stipend, University of Wyoming	2005
Computer Science, Engineering, and Mathematics Scholarship, University of Wyoming	2005
Honors Program, University of Wyoming	2005

## **Professional Service**

Executive Service in Professional Organizations

Program Coordinator	The Wildlife Society
Native Student Professional Development Grant	2018 – Present
Secretary/Treasurer	The Wildife Society
CENTRAL MOUNTAINS AND PLAINS SECTION	2018 – 2021
Working Group Membership	
Rangeland Wildlife Working Group, The Wildlife Society	2018 – Present
Native Peoples' Wildlife Management Working Group, The Wildlife Society	2015 – Present
Student Development Working Group, The Wildlife Society	2013 – Present

## Chapter Membership

Central Mountains and Plains Section, The Wildlife Society	2018 – Present
Kansas Chapter, The Wildlife Society	2015 – Present
South Dakota Chapter, The Wildlife Society	2014 – 2017
Nebraska Chapter, The Wildlife Society	2013 – 2014
Chadron State Student Chapter, The Wildlife Society	2012 – 2013

#### Professional Organization Membership

Society for Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics and Native Americans in Science	2021 – Present
Gamma Sigma Delta Honor Society	2019 – Present
American Indian Science and Engineering Society	2019 – Present
Swift Fox Conservation Team	2018 – Present
Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society	2016 – Present
Native American Fish and Wildlife Society	2015 – Present
Rocky Mountain Bighorn Society	2015 – 2017
Wild Sheep Foundation	2014 – 2020
American Society of Mammalogists	2013 – Present
The Wildlife Society	2013 – Present

#### External Journal Reviewer

Journal of Mammalogy, PeerJ, Canadian Journal of Zoology

### **Presentations**

#### Contributed

- 15. Palomo-Muñoz, G., **T.J. Werdel**, C.W. Piper, M. Fidno, A.M. Ricketts, and A.A. Ahlers. **2022**. Local-scale habitat structure mediates interactions between coyotes and lagamorphs. *101st Annual Meeting of the American Society of Mammalogists, Tucson, AZ*.
- 14. **Werdel, T.J.**, C.W. Piper, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2021**. Scale-specific landscape effects impose range-limiting constraints on the distribution of swift foxes. *The Wildlife Society 28th Annual Conference, Virtual*.
- 13. Piper, C.W, **T.J. Werdel**, A.M. Ricketts, D. Sullins, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2021**. Landscape composition and proximity to water structure American badger distributions in shortgrass prairies. *The Wildlife Society 28th Annual Conference, Virtual*.
- 12. **Werdel, T.J.**, C.W. Piper, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2021**. Multiscale landscape effects impose range-limiting constraints on the distribution of swift fox. *Swift Fox Conservation Team Meeting, Virtual*.
- 11. **Werdel, T.J.**, C.W. Piper, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2021**. Multiscale landscape effects impose range-limiting constraints on the distribution of swift fox. *Midwest Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies Furbearer Workshop, Virtual*.
- 10. Piper, C.W, **T.J. Werdel**, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2021**. Landscape composition and proximity to water structure American badger (*Taxidea taxus*) distributions in shortgrass prairies. *Midwest Association of Fish and Wildlife Agencies Furbearer Workshop, Virtual*.
- 9. **Werdel, T.J.**, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2020**. Assessing factors that influence occupancy and colonization of swift fox in western Kansas. *Kansas Natural Resources Conference, Manhattan, KS*.
- 8. **Werdel, T.J.**, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2019**. Assessing factors that shape carnivore diversity in shortgrass prairie ecosystems. *American Fisheries Society and The Wildlife Society 2019 Joint Annual Conference, Reno, NV*.
- 7. **Werdel, T.J.**, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2019**. Carnivore richness and diversity is driven by landscape change in shortgrass prairie ecosystems. **99th Annual Meeting of the American Society of Mammalogists, Washington, D.C**.
- 6. **Werdel, T.J.**, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2019**. Landscape effects on swift fox occupancy in western Kansas. *Southwest/Midwest Joint Furbearer Meeting, Enid, OK*.
- 5. **Werdel, T.J.**, A.M. Ricketts, and A.A. Ahlers. **2019**. Landscape change structures carnivore communities in shortgrass prairie ecosystems. *Kansas Natural Resources Conference, Manhattan, KS*.
- 4. **Werdel, T.J.**, A.M. Ricketts, M. Peek, and A.A. Ahlers. **2018**. Assessing the spatial distribution of swift fox in western Kansas. *The Wildlife Society 25th Annual Conference, Cleveland, OH*.
- 3. **Werdel, T.J.**, J.A. Jenks. **2018**. Survival of bighorn sheep in the Deadwood region of the Black Hills. *Nebraska/Central Mountains and Plains Section of The Wildlife Society Annual Meeting, Kearney, NE*.
- 2. **Werdel, T.J.**, J.A. Jenks, J. Kanta, and C. Lehman. **2016**. Evaluation of the Deadwood bighorn sheep herd translocation. *The Wildlife Society 23rd Annual Conference, Raleigh, NC*.
- 1. **Werdel, T.J.**. **2013**. Small mammal population and diversity in relation to prairie dog reintroduction sites. **Sevilleta LTER Research Experience for Undergraduates Summer Symposium, Socorro, NM**.

<b>Bighorn Sheep Capture and Monitoring Techniques</b> KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY	Manhattan, KS 2022
Applied Wildlife Management: A Landscape Ecology Approach TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY	College Station, TX 2021
Traditional Ecological Knowledge: A Place-Based Perspective TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY	College Station, TX 2021
<b>Distribution of Swift Fox in Kansas</b> Kansas Department of Wildlife, Parks and Tourism	Emporia, KS 2021
Traditional Ecological Knowledge (TEK) of Wetlands KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY	Manhattan, KS 2021
Bighorn Sheep Capture and Monitoring Techniques Kansas State University	Manhattan, KS 2021
Wild Sheep Natural History Kansas State University	Manhattan, KS 2021
Bighorn Sheep Capture and Monitoring Techniques KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY	Manhattan, KS 2020
Traditional Ecological Knowledge (TEK) of Wetlands KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY	Manhattan, KS 2019
Keynote Speaker: Youth Wildlife Conservation Experience WILD SHEEP FOUNDATION SHEEP SHOW	Reno, NV 2019
Inclusive Pedagogy Student Panel The WILDLIFE SOCIETY ANNUAL CONFERENCE	Cleveland, OH 2018
Bighorn Sheep Monitoring Kansas State University	Manhattan, KS 2018
Marlatt STEM Night Marlatt Elementary School	Manhattan, KS 2018
Initiating a Student Chapter of The Wildlife Society HASKELL INDIAN NATIONS UNIVERSITY	Lawrence, KS 2018
Toyota STEM Speaker Red Cloud Indian School	Pine Ridge, SD 2016
<b>Deadwood Bighorn Sheep Translocation</b> SOUTH DAKOTA GAME, FISH, AND PARKS	Rapid City, SD 2015
<b>Bighorn Sheep and Community Interaction</b> KIWANIS CLUB	Lead, SD 2015
Graduate School Experience and Preparation CHADRON STATE COLLEGE	Chadron, NE 2015
Project WILD, Children and Wildlife RED CLOUD INDIAN SCHOOL	Pine Ridge, SD 2013